ok,我们接下来要学习什么呢？让我们从一个典型的
Okay, what are the rules that we're going
to follow? Well, let's start with looking
排序问题开始吧。假如某个大学有许多信息学生记录
at a typical basic sorting problem. Say,
university has student records and for
每一个学生都有一定数量的信息。也许是班级序号、
every student there is a certain amount of
information. Maybe there's a class number,
成绩、电话号码或者地址。因此我们引用一项纪录，
there is a grade, there's a phone number
maybe an address so we refer to an item
这项纪录有我们将要排序的信息或者记录。但是
and it has a record or the information
that we're going to sort. But in
实际上，记录的某一部分叫做关键字，我们将做的工作就是
particular, there's a piece of a record
called a key and what we want to do is put
根据这些关键字来排序记录。这就是排序问题。
the records into order according to the
key. That's the sort problem. Re-arrange
根据每一项的关键字，重新升序排列一个n项的数组
an array of n items into ascending order
according to a defined key which is part
现在我们的目标是能够排序任何类型的数据，因此让我们
of the item. Now, our goal is to be able
to sort any type of data so let's look at
来看两个程序。第一个例子是升序排列一些随机的实数
a couple of client programs. First example
is to just sort some random real numbers
看，这儿有一个客户端来调用我们的插入排序方法，它先
into ascending order. So, here's a client
that calls our insertion sort method and
从标准输入读取数据到一个数组，然后调用插入排序
all it does is read numbers from standard
input than into an array a then calls
最后把排序后数组打印出来。在右边，你能看见
insertion sort and then prints them out.
And you can see on the right that the
这些数按顺序被打印出来了。这个看起来像是一个
numbers are printed out in sorted order.
This seems like an artificial kind of
人工的输入，但是我们在接下来会看见一个程序。
input but actually we'll look at an
application even in this lecture. And then
在一些程序里，随机输入时比较好的输入模型。排序字符串也许是
there are many applications where random
inputs are fine model. Here's maybe a more
更加常见的排序形式。在这种形式下，它使用我们的
familiar sort client that sort strings.
And in this case it reads the strings from
In类中的readString()方法从文件中读入字符串，
a file using our readStrings() method in
our In class that which takes a file as
这方法需要一个文件为参数。所以我们将这个文件名作为第一个
argument. So we take the file name as the
first command line argument, read in array
命令行参数，从文件中读取字符串到数组中，再一次调用Insertion.sort()方法。
of string from that file separated by
blanks, call an Insertion.sort() method again. So,
因此，Insertion.sort是一个需要一个数组作为参数的方法
Insertion.sort is a method that takes an
array a as its parameter and it, it's the
这个方法会将这个数组重新排序。在这个例子中，words three.txt
first argument and it rearranges the
strings in that array to be in sorted
文件中有一些三个字母的单词，然后这个客户端程序
order. So in this case words, words
three.text has the certain number of three
将按照字母序重新排列那些三字母单词。
letter words and this client program will
result in those three letter words being
如果我们完成了能够排序任何类型数据的目标的话，
rearranged into alphabetical order.
Here's another client that we could use
这儿是另一个能够使用我们的排序代码的客户端程序。
our sort program for, if we achieved the
goal of sorting any type of data. In this
在这个程序中，我们将要排序给定的一些文件的名字。
one, we're going to sort file, file's name
in a given directory. So again we use the
我们将再一次使用Java中的File类，我们使用这个类，
File class from Java and we use, we go and
use the listFiles() method from that class
然后得到一个包含一些给定文件的文件名数组。那是一个存储
to get an array that contains all the file
names in the given directory. That's an
文件名的数组。Insertion.sort()方法需要数组作为第一个
array with file names in it and Insertion.sort()
takes that array as its first
参数，然后将他们排序。然后我们继续，最后遍历并将
argument and again sorts them and then we
go ahead and use as, go through them one
他们一个个打印出来，最后的结果是按照文件名的顺序给出。
by one and print them and they come out in
order of file name. So that's three
ok，这就是三个不同的客户端程序，三个完全不同类型的数据。
different clients, three completely
different types of data. And the first
我们不得不思考的这个游戏的第一条规则就是
rule of the game that we have to think
about is, how can we make it so that we
我们怎么实现一个能够被三个不同的客户端程序使用去
can implement one sort program that can be
used by these three different clients to
排序三种不同类型数据的排序程序。在这种情况下
implement three different types of data.
In the way that, that happens is a
一种被称为回调的机制就很有用。因此，我们的
mechanism known as a callback. So, that's
our basic question, how can sort, now, how
基本的问题是就由怎么排序变为怎么在不给出关键字的类型信息
to compare data of all those different
types without being given any information
时去比较这些不同类型的数据。答案就是我们制定
about the type of an item's key? And the
answer is that what is we set up a
一个被称为回调的机制，或者说是一个在客户端程序可
mechanism known as a callback or reference
to executable code where the client, by
执行代码的引用的机制。在Java里面，有一个隐形
passing an array of objects to the sort
function. In Java, there's an implicit
机制，这个机制就是说一些存储对象的数组需要有
mechanism that says that any such array of
object is going to have the compareTo()
compareTo()方法，然后这个排序函数将调用数组元素
method, then the sort function calls back
the compareTo() method associated with the
的compareTo方法当需要的时候，或者是说需要来比较
objects in the array when it ever needs,
whenever it needs to compare two items.
两个元素的时候。有许多不同的方式来实现回调，那是
There's a lot of different ways to
implement callbacks and that's
编程语言规范决定的。不同的语言有不同的机制。核心
programming language specific. Different
languages have different mechanisms. It's
思想就是将函数作为一个参数传递给其他的函数，这个是结对
all about the idea of passing functions as
arguments to other functions which is the
出现的，回想一下函数式编程和邱奇-图灵理论。
pair and gets into functional programming
and thinking all the way back to Turing and
对于Java,因为有编译时类型检查，所以这个回调机制
Church. For Java, because of the desire
to check types at compile time, the use of
的用法被称为一个接口，接下来我们将讨论使用java接口
specific method called an interface and
then, we'll look at the details of how to
来实现回调的细节。这些内容有点涉及到编程语言
implement callbacks with the Java
interfaces now. It's a little bit of
的细节，但是这是值得去讨论的。因为它允许我们
programming language detailed but it's,
it's really worthwhile because it allows
用一种类型安全的方式，使用自己开发的排序算法来排序任何类型的数据。
us to use the sorts that we developed for
any type of data in a type safe manner. So
因此我们已经看过了一些客户端程序。这是排序文件名的
we already looked at some clients. This is
the example of the client program that
客户端程序例子。它调用我们的sort()方法，并传递了
sorts the files in a given directory by
file name. So it just calls our sort()
一个某种类型的数组作为第一个参数。现在，Java语言内置
method with a, an array some type of
object as first argument. Now, built in to
的是一个被称为Comparable的接口，所有的实现comparable接口
Java is the so-called the Comparable
interface and all the Comparable interface
都任何数据类型都将实现一个compareTo()方法。
is the specification that a type, data
type that implements Comparable will have
它是泛型的，将同确定类型的元素进行比较。
a compareTo() method. And it's generic and
will be compared to against a certain type
现在我们将让那些需要排序的对象都实现comparable接口。
of item. Now when we implement objects
that are to be sorted we'll implement the
那是顶级类文件实现comparable接口。
Comparable method. That's up in the top
class file, implements comparable file.
因为排序是一种常见的操作，一些常用的标准
And since sorting is an operation that's
used in so many situations, many of the
Java类也实现了Comparable接口。
standard Java types that you would expect
to involve sorts will implement
也就是说实现了comparable接口的那些类的
Comparable. And all that means is that,
that data type has an instance method that
实例都实现了compareTo方法，它根据一些
will implement the compareTo() method.
It'll compare this object against the
复杂的比较规则来比较方法参数给出的对象和自身对象
object given as argument and depending on
some complicated tests, it'll return -1,
返回-1代表小于或者少于，+1代表着大于或多余，0代表相等
meaning less, +1, meaning greater or
0, meaning equal. Now, that compareTo()
compareto方法是所有排序实现所必须的方法。
method is really all that the sort
implementation needs. First it says that,
首先，假如说，某种排序实现需要一个元素为Comparable类型的数组
that it's going to take as argument an
array of type Comparable. So that means,
作为参数，这就意味着数组里面的元素将实现Comparable接口
the objects in the array are going to
implement the Comparable interface or that
或者是说会有一个compareTo方法。然后排序代码
it will have a compareTo() method. And then
the sort code can just use that compareTo()
能够在数组中的某个元素上调用取compareTo方法
method, invoked in a sense of the
object like an entry in the array and as
并将另一个数组元素作为参数传入，以此来测试
argument and another instance in the
object like another entry in the array to
是否前者小于后者，正如这个例子所展示的一样。
test whether the first is less than the
second as in this example. The key point
关键的是排序实现并没有依赖所排序数据
is that the sort implementation has no
dependence on the type of data that's
的类型，不同的Comparable数组都将以同样的
handled by the Comparable interface and a
different Comparable array will be sorted
逻辑被排序，因为接口机制，最后他们实际回调待排对象
in the same way though eventually, because
of the interface mechanism, they call back
的compareTo方法。现在有几条很简单
to the actual compareTo() code that goes
with a type of object being sorted. Now
规则，但是值得我们去讨论和关注这些规则。
there's a few rules and there's natural
rules but they're worth talking about and
那就是compareTo方法必须满足全序顺序。
paying attention to that the compareTo()
method has to implement in the so called a
总的来说就是，通过排序，总是能够将待排序项
total order. In all that saying is really
that it must be possible to put items in
排列有序。因此，存在三个性质。第一个
order in a sort. So there's three
properties. First one says that if v is
如果v <= w，w <= v，那么 v == w，第二就是传递性
less than or equal to w and w is less than
or equal to v then the only way for that
如果v <= w， w <= x，那么 v <= x。
to be true is if they're equal and then
there's transitivity. If v less than w, w
第三就是，v 与 w的关系之后三种，
is less than x, then v must be less than
or equal to x. In totality, is that either
v is less than or equal to w or w is less
than equal to v or both they are equal.
在我们想作为排序关键字的数据类型中，有许多
And there's plenty of natural total orders
in the types of data that we normally want
种自然全排序。比如说整数、自然数、实数序，或者字符串
to consider for sort keys. Like the
integers or natural numbers or real
的字母序，日期或时间的日历序等等。
numbers or alphabetical order for strings,
chronological order for dates or times and
右边的卡通表明不是所有的顺序都必须是全排序。
so forth. The cartoon on the right shows
that not all orders are necessarily total
全序。比如，rock，paper，scissors不具有传递性。如果已知 v < w，
orders. So, rock, paper, scissors is intransitive.
If you know that v is less
w < v，不能得出v <= v。对不起，
that w, w is less than v, you don't know
that v is less than or equal to v. I'm
（如果已知）v < w，w <= x，并不能得出
sorry, v is less than w, w less than equal
to x that you don't necessarily know that
v <= x。好。接下来讲Comparable接口，按照惯例，
v is less than or equal to x. Alright. So
the Comparable API then, by convention in
在Java中我们总是需要实现compareTo()方法，以使 v与w满足
Java we always need to implement compareTo()
such that v that compared to w is a
全序。而且，同样根据惯例，小于返回一个负整数，
total order. And also by convention, it
returns a negative integer for its less
等于返回0，大于返回正整数。如果该对象大于
zero if it's equal positive its greater.
If this object is greater than the object
作为参数的对象。如果对象类型不兼容或某一对象为空，
given as argument. If the types are
incompatible or if either one is null
compareTo()方法应该抛出异常。再次说明，Java中许多
compareTo() should throw an exception.
Now, again, many of Java's standard types
存储数值、日期、文件等的标准数据类型通常都会实现compareTo()方法。
for numbers and dates and files and so
forth implement compareTo() by convention.
根据这些原则，如果我们要比较自己的数据类型，那么我们必须
Now if we're going to implement our own
type then we have to go ahead and
实现Comparable接口。一般来讲
implement the Comparable interface
according to these rules. And usually
这一点是很明确的。所以来看这个例子。这是Java内部Date类的简化版，
that's fairly straightforward. So here's
an example. It's a simplified version of
为了展示实现Comparable接口的思想。
the Date class that's implemented within
Java just to show the idea of implementing
首先，我们在类声明之后写上implements
Comparable. So, after the class
declaration, we write implements
***Comparable，然后。。。因为我们仅仅是
Comparable and then we fill in the generic
with the same type because we're only
与另一个日期比较。在此接口实现中，Date类有
going to compare dates to other dates. In
this implementation, the Date class has
三个实例变量，month，day，year，并且像你们看到的，构造函数
three instance variables. The month, the
day and the year and the constructor
将参数值赋给它们。所以现在，如果你想比较两个
fills those from the arguments as you can
see. So now, if you want to compare two
不同的日期，那么首先要做的是检查该年份是否小于
different dates then the first thing to do
is to check if this year is less than that
另一年份，通过比较年份，这两个日期存在几种情况。如果为真
year, over that is the year given, the
date given in the argument. If that's true
那么该年份小，返回-1，如果（为假）该年份大，返回+1。
then it's less return -1 and if it's,
the year is greater, return +1.
否则，这两个年份相等，我们必须通过月份来做
Otherwise, the year, years must be equal
so we have to look at the months to do the
比较，同理一直比较到日期。当且仅当年份、月份、日期均相等时
compare and so forth down to do the days.
Only if they're all equal that we return
返回0。这就是Comparable接口实现的例子，通过
zero. So, that's an example of an
implementation of Comparable by
实现compareTo()方法对日期排序。（总之，）
implementing the compareTo() method to put
dates in order as you might expect. So the
Java语言通过此Comparable接口机制让我们可以
Java language helps us with this
Comparable mechanism so that we can sort
对任何类型的数据排序。当我们接着实现排序算法时，
data of any type. When we continue to
implement sorting algorithms, we're
其实是在实现接口。这就是排序算法，
actually even in a hide that beneath our
own implementations. So, that are sorting
实际上它们的代码可以用来在许多其他语言中实现排序。
algorithms actually their actual code can
be used to implement sorting in many other
方式是采取两个主要操作——比较和
languages. The way we do that is to take
the two primary operations, compares and
交换——来引用数据，并把这两个操作封装成
exchangers that were that were, were used
to refer the data and encapsulate them
两个静态方法。所以，我们使用一个less()方法，它需要两个
just the static methods. So, we're going
to use a method less() that takes two
可比较的对象作为参数并且返回，v.compareTo(w)小于0。
Comparable objects as arguments and it
just returns, v.compareTo(w) less than
然后，对数组元素排序时另一件要做的事是
zero. And then the other thing that we do
when we sort items that are in an array is
将索引为i和j的数组元素相交换。
to, to swap or exchange of the item at a
given index i with the one at a given
这是每一个程序员首次接触赋值语句就会的。
index j. And that's every programmer's
first introduction to assignment
将a[i]存到变量swap，把a[j]赋给a[i]，再把 swap存回
statements. We save a[i] in a variable swap,
put a[j] in a[i], and then put swap back
到a[j]。因此现在，使用我们的排序方法引用数据将只使用这两个静态
in a[j]. So now our sort methods to refer
the data will just use this two static
方法。而且有一个很好的理由。下面是一个例子。假设我们想
methods. And there's a good reason for
that. Here's an example. Suppose we want
测试一个数组是否已排序。那么这是一个静态的方法，数组已排序返回真，
to test if an array is sorted. So this is
a static method that is supposed to return
否则返回假。它所做的只是遍历数组
true if the array is sorted and false if it's
not. And all it does is just go through
检查是否每个元素都小于
the array from the one to the length of
the array and test if each item is less
上一个元素。如果存在某元素小于上一个元素那么该数组
than the one before. If you have an item
that's less than one before then it's not
未排好序，返回假。遍历数组都没有这种情况，
sorted you return false. If you get all
the way through the array without that
那么数组已排序。这是非常简单的代码，问题是，
happening, then you say the array is true.
That's pretty simple code, the question
如果你有一个排序算法（经此算法排序的数组）通过了测试，你能肯定它
is, if you have a sorting algorithm that
passes that test, are you sure that it
就正确地排序了数组吗？ 答案是，是的如果，如果
correctly sorted the array? Well the
answer to that question is, yes if, yes if
你只是用less()和exchange()方法实现、引用数据，
you used only the less() and exchange()
methods to implement, to refer the data
因为那样你知道，你用的exchange()方法数组排序后的数据
because then you know because you used the
exchange() method that the data in the array
和排序前的数据一样。如果你
after the sort is the same data as was in
the array before the sort, sort. If you
有一种排序方法可以在数组中存储任何值，例如
have a sort method that can store any
values in an array, it could, for example,
将每个数组元素存为0，该排序方法（排序的结果）同样能通过测试，但是它不是
store zeros in every array entry that
method would pass this test, but it didn't
正确的数组排序，因为它重写了数组元素值。所以我们使用less()
really correctly sort the array because
overwrote all the values. So, we use less()
和exchange()方法，确保可以用这种方法测试我们的排序结果。
and exchange() to be sure that we can test
that our, our methods work with the method
like this.